so just to bring you back up to date we
were uh we we were thinking to do this
little teaching
here and my teacher it took him 20 years
to finish it for us and we were thinking
to have that time since we're Americans
we can do things
fastly so uh we thought maybe 10 years
would be
enough and uh we had a plan
to uh C this is a book called L
CH which means uh the steps of the path
to Enlightenment so the
theory yeah sorry the theory is that uh
you study one by one uh certain
spiritual realizations like for example
a meditation on the fact that you will
have to die one day or meditation on on
loving every living creature in this
world and and those
meditations uh are arranged in a special
order and the idea is that if you if
someone takes you through them slowly
properly then you can learn all the
steps to becoming an enlightened being
uh then there's a custom called the
yamry where
you you study each meditation but then
you don't go on until you all get it uh
until you all internalize it and so I
I've known some La room teachers who
started on step number one and then 30
years later all their students were
still on step number one and the teacher
passed away and that was the end of it
but
um uh the idea for for this series of
teachings uh is that we would uh learn
one step at a time from the steps of the
path to enlightening and then we would
uh go on a retreat together uh in some
quiet place out in the forest and for 10
days and try to internalize that
teaching so the the plan is twice a year
to do the theory the book uh in a
setting like this one and then twice a
year following that maybe a month two
months later to go together on a solid
Retreat for 10 days and work really hard
on internalizing that teaching
to really appreciate each of the steps
or to internalize them requires that you
meditate
the the section on meditation is one of
the last sections of the whole book uh
because inet it would be assumed that
you were pretty good at meditating
already uh so what we we are planned for
this series of classic courses which
will take 10 years is that we'll go to
the back first uh study the detailed
instructions there on how to
medicate and then the next uh section
after that which is very famous uh it's
a section
about how reality really works how
things really work where where where do
the people and things around you really
come from and how can
you help the world change the world
bring peace to the world remove poverty
illness War
from the world uh by tweaking reality so
there's a section on tweaking reality I
like to think of the Mak where keano
Reeves who's never figured out
anything uh he figures out that uh he
figures out that the world is a is like
a computer program and then he he tweaks
it and and I I enjoy that uh you guys
I I enjoy the scene at the end where
he's you know he just figured out how to
triak reality somebody shoots a gun at
him and then instead of ducking he just
holds out his hand and I guess he does
something with the binary code that runs
the program that's running his world and
then the bullets just drop to the ground
so we're trying to do something similar
we're actually we're doing something
extremely similar we're trying
to use deep states of meditation to be
able to see into the code that underlies
reality itself and then do tweaking of
that reality to stop War
hunger uh illness and DEP itself that's
the idea okay a small
undertaking
uh so we we are going to be studying in
this course uh the meditation part which
you need to access the code right to get
deep down enough into the into the world
to see the code you have to be in deep
meditation you can't uh you can't break
the code really unless you can go very
deeply into meditation so we we are
going to study that first and then we
were going to study uh the code itself
and how to manipulate the code of
reality and then after that we were
going to go back and start
book uh step one to the last step and
apply the meditation and the tweaking of
reality to each of the steps of the path
to Enlightenment all
right so we're starting at the back
first and then we'll go back to the
beginning and then you know 8 years from
now or six years from now will be out of
the back of the book back of the book
will have been done already so then
we're going to skip to another text
uh which was written uh in 1409
something like that uh by the teacher of
his Hol the first D and in that book uh
he he gives much greater detail about
how to tweak the reality so we'll you
know six seven years from now when we're
done with this book uh having already
been through the last part about
tweaking uh we'll switch to a even more
famous book on tweaking right and
that'll be 400 pages of tweaking all
right so that will take a while right
and I just think it's a nice way to
spend your life for 10
years uh the the the whole book is full
of beautiful beautiful practices for
conducting your life and helping other
people you know things like
patience and how to live an ethical life
how to be generous to other people
things like that how to generate Joy
how to generate compassion so all of
those subjects will be studying under
the microscope of deep meditation and
and an understanding of how reality
works
so there are a lot of people who are
just flying into the teaching on the
weekends uh I think there were about 50
people more or something I don't know
and then they uh I sort of wanted them
to hear all of the meditation part
uninterrupted so we did half of it last
weekend we'll be doing the other half of
it next weekend we did not cover any of
homework for those of you who've been
struggling with
[Music]
it all right sorry I should have told
you right uh but I hope you figured it
out maybe you just had some good time at
the
cafe so tonight we're going to skip to
class
six uh so for five will get on the
weekend uh with the other guyss to learn
more about uh how to meditate right so
what we're going to do while they're
away is start the final section on
tweaking reality right how to tweak
reality I'd like to give just I talked
about it the other day but I'd like to
repeat it uh on was it Monday yesterday
we uh we did like I don't know five
hours of uh a very very Advanced book on
it's it's the text from my own Monastery
that was written 500 years ago on you
know it was an advanced manual on
tweaking and I've been doing that book
for seven years with some of my students
and I think it will take another 10 or
14 years so uh we were working on that
text uh just because we have to do that
every few months so they're never going
to finish and we had an extra day uh on
Monday and so during those classes I I
did a short demonstration and I talked
about uh the idea of tweaking I'd like
to just do it again for five
minutes and then uh we'll then we'll
jump
into uh this explanation which is by
uh which was written it was taught or in
over a 24 day period by PAB R who is the
teacher of
CH who is the teacher of the current
Bama and CH was also the teacher of my
teacher my teacher also met p uh when he
was a
teenager and B there's a beautiful story
that my teacher had just been
[Music]
appointed
of concept so is one of the colleges
like Oxford has colleges right Yong is
one of the colleges of Sarah monaster
Sarah is one of the greatest it's one of
the big three monasteries of Tibet it
had about 10,000 months then it has 12
colleges and and youron college is is my
college and it's my teacher's college
and it was P's College you see so we own
p and uh and he came to give a talk like
this at at get com and you know
sponsored it uh in the in the in the
late
1930s and and my teacher was a teenager
in and then there's a there's a
beautiful story that my teacher was at
the time very
naughty uh for example in Tibet the
monks uh took their shoes off at the
door of the monastery the monastery was
a small City uh it had 10,000 people in
it but the monks would take their shoes
off at the door of the monastery at the
front gate of the monaster so one of the
typical things my teacher enjoyed doing
was spreading thumb tacks all over
the uh opening of the day and uh then
they he had a special skill at a thing
called f say
b b is two words
and okay and b means uh D like cookie
dough call from
so b means do da means a spear or or a
projectile so my teacher K he was known
for his skill at Banga Banga means
you're sitting in a huge assembly of
monks with like 3,000 monks from your
college and everyone's chanting uh these
deep T you know
and you know and then he would wait
until the guy's mouth was open and then
he he'
go and uh there'd be this contest to see
if you could if the guy was like over
there like if you could hit him right in
the mouth and then he'd be choking on
and uh he was like number one in
pla and
uh and he was really good at AC innocent
uh so the people around him would always
get in trouble and he wouldn't get in
trouble and then he was headed towards
being a cook in the monaster which is
what happens to
pong it's probably some kind of karma to
be a cook at our Monastery is no small
thing I mean the pot you can climb into
the pot like if they put you to cleaning
that pot it takes like four or five
hours and uh so he was on his way to
being a cook then he met B
came to his house and and my teacher was
neara means he got stuck being Quarter
Master of the House like he has to watch
over how many bags of butter they Yak
butter they have he has to keep count of
them and like that so he was near but
that means he got to meet who came to
check out the refreshments before he
gave the talk
and uh then there's a story that he held
my teacher's head in his
hands and and he said uh inser it means
this
one this one I think this one will turn
out well right I think this one will be
good he just held his head like that and
then he he went on and gave his teaching
and then from that day something
happened in R's mind and uh he became uh
when had the final debates when he
graduated with his G out of 10,000 monks
he was number
one he did he he defeated 10,000 monks
in
debate and in the the final debate is
held in the damus personal
quarters so he did meet Pap and he got
this blessing and he received teachings
on
this so I just want to demonstrate just
just one small demonstration
from which pretty much summarizes
everything you're going to hear for the
next 5
days uh because I struggled with
emptiness for a long time in the
monastery and uh you know I told a story
the other day that my teacher challenged
me to meditate about
emptiness and I had read all these books
about emptiness none of which was
correct and they're still not correct in
English and uh one of them said
emptiness was just close your eyes and
everything is black one of them said
emptiness means don't think about
anything one of them said emptiness
means everything's an illusion and it
doesn't matter whether you're nice to
people or you're hurt people and these
are all very serious mistakes about the
nature of the computer program you see
it's not true that the ultimate meaning
of life is a is a black hole and it's
not true that you get to the ultimate
meaning of Life by sitting and thinking
about nothing and staring at a wall and
it's not true that the ultimate meaning
of life is everything is illusion and it
doesn't matter in fact quite the
opposite right everything depends on how
kind you are to other
people so really the big leap that you
have to make is how do you tie an
understanding of the Ultimate Reality of
of all things to kindness towards other
people I why why is there a
connection between the way reality
really works and kindness towards other
people where do compassion and Ultimate
Reality meet okay and you can understand
it in like five minutes and then we'll
go through this beautiful text and
you'll understand it again at the end
all right so here we go again what is
this
thing yeah it's a pen uh if a dog came
into into this room and I I always
picture them at this moment a little
puppy dog my teacher loved uh dogs he
always had puppies running around and if
a puppy cuz he wasn't allowed to have
one in the monastery so he had many uh
and and if the puppy dog comes up and we
wave this pen what will the dog do so he
will take it in his mouth and he'll chew
on
it so to the dog this is not a pen it's
a you call it a chew T okay it's
something to chew
on to the human it's a head so then some
philosophical questions AR us who's
right yeah I think you have to say both
you can't say uh the human is more right
than the dog in the end you know humans
like to say the dog ruined my pen but I
imagine the dog is thinking that guy's
wasting a perfectly good true to you
know uh you know you can't really say
that one more right than I don't you
know obviously you can't say that that
one of them is wrong right one is seeing
one thing according to their own context
and one is seeing a different thing in
the same room at the same time with the
same thing you see you can almost well
not almost you can you can say that
there are two realities running in the
room at the same time there's a dog's
reality running in the room parallel
universes physicists are up to what 17
now something
uh but actually there are as many worlds
in this room there are as many rooms in
this room as there are people because
each person is seeing a different room
right so another question for
you if I put this object down on the
stage uh and if we all leave the room
and if there are no dogs in the room
then what is
it somebody said nothing I mean or you
could say it's just a black it's a black
cylinder or something like that but it's
definitely it's not either one of those
other things by itself right when the
human walks in and they they they kind
of lay a trip on it it becomes a pen
when the dog comes in and chews on it it
becomes a chew toy if there's no humans
and no dogs and you just set it on the
on on the steps here then it's it's not
really anything until someone comes in
right so next question for
you is the pen coming this way or is the
pen coming this
way
sorry yeah from us yeah it's coming from
us right you can we agree you got to nod
or you can't go home yes all right my
teacher said if you don't no you don't
get home all right it it is it must be
coming this way all right right because
the dog sees a choid
validly and the human sees a pen validly
so it must be coming this way if it were
coming this way then either the human
would be salivating or the dog would be
riding right if it were either a shw toy
or a pen this way from from its own side
then the dog the dog would write with it
or else both of them would would chew on
it you see if it were something in a in
itself coming this way so it its
existence as a pen depends
on my mind making it into a pen okay
next question is that a conscious
process did you when I held this up did
you think oh let let me think of it as a
pen and then I can write with it did you
have to think that way no you didn't
have to think that way if you really
wanted it to be something else could you
close your eyes think hard wish hard if
you wanted it to be a a stick of diamond
right could you just close your eyes and
wish real hard and then you you want to
try here we go close your eyes wish that
it was a big diamond I'll split it with
you the
[Music]
proper okay open your eyes what is
the so it is coming from your mind but
that's not under your current conscious
control okay it is coming from your mind
but you can't say to yourself oh I want
it to be a diamond or I want it to be a
gold stick or something like that right
it is coming from your mind but there's
some kind of for you're forced to see it
in a certain
way now how do we explain that how do we
explain that in how did Lord Buddha
explain it uh Karma okay he explain it
like what does Karm
me uh let's say Rebecca needs a pen all
right you need a pen right she really
needs a pen because she forgot to bring
her pen to take notes apparently and um
and so I I want to help her all right I
want her to to have a pen I like these
pens you know I actually these are hard
to
find uh I really like them you know uh
so but I'm going to give it away to her
because uh I love her and I I want her
to be happy right so then I I I I reach
out to give her a pen the mind is like a
video camera the Mind records everything
you say everything you think everything
you ever do in your whole life is
permanently recorded in your mind right
like a huge hard disk that's why people
get confused and see now late in their
life because there's so much data in
there all right built up overbuilt up so
when I release the pen with the
intention to help her a seed is planted
in my mind right you can s you can say
our kic seed is planted in my mind in in
the recesses of the Mind within the
subconscious that seed like all other
seeds grows exponentially its power
multiplies exponentially right like an
acorn right me just consider that an
acorn which weighs one GR
in time produces a oak tree which weighs
tons right it's extraordinary ability to
replicate itself under the ground from
under the ground right mental seeds are
no less powerful in fact they're more
powerful So within the
subconscious the the perception and the
imprint made by offering her a pen uh
exponentially multiplies under the
ground of the conscious mind and then uh
I'm able to see many pens later right if
you offer someone one pen a gift of one
pen uh you will receive many pens back
you will you will see many pens okay
that's why you see a pen when I hold up
that thing I need a b sorry it's Indian
here so the the reason you saw a pen
when I held it up was that there there
was a seed in your mind for a pen that
seed was planted by offering a writing
instrument to another person who needed
one or some similar kind of kindness all
right that's true of every person you
ever met and that's true of every object
you ever saw in every Church you ever
sat in and every carpet you ever sat on
and every air conditioner that blue on
you what is it all cranked down by the
way uh I mean every everything that you
experience in your life around you each
different object and each different
person has been produced by a separate
seed they are
coming this way right they are coming
this way and and whether you like them
whether they're nice or they're not nice
whether the place is hot or cold uh
whether the carpet is soft or or hard
it's all coming from you it's all coming
from how much kindness you've paid to
other people so we can see that
compassion and the world are actually
linked together see how you treat other
people has created every detail of the
world around you and of your own body
and mind you
see if I'm blessed with a healthy body
if I'm blessed to see this body is
healthy it's because I have served other
people okay sick people and the whole
world is like that so
emptiness
means if you took away all the seeds in
my
mind and if you took away all the
kindnesses I had paid to other people
what would this
be it would just be a black stick you
see I wouldn't see it as a
pen it can only be a pen if I have been
kind to other people by itself it's like
a blank white screen and everything in
the world is the same every person you
ever met that wasn't nice and they
weren't mean either they were just black
white screens they were neutral If you
experience them as kind it's because
you've been kind to other people seeds
are ripening in your mind to see them as
kind and if you see them as unpleasant
then then that's because you've been
unpleasant to other people last thing
then we can go to the book which just
tells you all this in 100
Pages uh
how do you get to
heaven
then how do you get to heaven
then
H yeah you just go crazy taking care of
other people you plant you consciously
plant
wildly huge amounts of seeds from being
kind to other people if you have a
person in your life that you don't
like which most of us do right at least
one right if there's somebody in your
life who's bothering you or hurting you
then you can change that by removing the
seed in your mind which was planted
there when you were not nice to somebody
else right so there is such a method of
removing negative seeds from your mind
if you removed all the negative seeds
from your mind that cause you to see
people and places as unpleasant then
every
single place and every single person you
ever met would be
pleasant if if you
were as kind as God to every living
being right if you planted seeds on that
level then you would start to see the
people around you as as
Angelic and you would be in heaven right
here you see don't have to go somewhere
there's a joke in tobet that you
Heaven's not like 3 miles past the back
of the Moon something okay
you you would just be seeing pens
instead of D what do you call two toce
right you would graduate from seeing Cho
to seeing penss you would graduate from
seeing normal people to seeing angels
and then you wouldn't be in heaven all
right that's the reason we're studying
reality tweaking methods is to reach
heaven and bring other people there in
the process hunger poverty War
death itself are erased from this
Earth it's it's
cool and that's why we're here and
that's what we're trying to achieve here
we go
ready so this begins uh class
six we'll go back to class four and five
on Friday and Sunday
uh you got to do your homeworks please
okay uh if you're one or two behind
catch up in the next tomorrow you have a
day off please catch up all right I
don't feel comfortable with people
teaching if they haven't completed all
their work and I I won't give you a
certificate if you don't complete all
your work because I don't feel
comfortable with you knowing half of it
or 3/4 of it or something like that or
not being able to express it to somebody
okay all the text is there the teaching
is there people have spent hundreds and
hundreds of hours to get you here the
Bears have you know know their whole
congregation has sweated to make this
place ready for you and all these people
are putting out all this effort you can
do a little bit of homework uh and then
you'll be qualified to teach it the
reason for me to teach it
personally I have a thousand other
things I'd like to be teaching but I
felt like if my teacher spent 20 years
loading this into me I would like to
offload it I would like to download it
to other people and I would like you to
become vessels of the same teaching and
then I would like you to see you create
other vessels of the same teaching so
I'm just really physically pouring it
into you and then what has to happen is
you have to pour it into somebody else
or the whole exercise is is useless you
know this book has been passed on the
alarm Rim has been passed
on for 9918 years all right are you
going to mess it up now you know are you
going to be the person who doesn't who
doesn't do their homework and doesn't
pass it on do you want to be responsible
for breaking a 98e
tradition I don't think so my work is
done when I teach you the last page then
your work begins actually next week uh
to pass it on to other people and I I
beg you to pass it on to other people
that's why we're here right so you have
to get it straight and you must pass it
on to other people because that's what
we're doing
then we can help the
world okay here we go you keep staying
here we
go so I'm reading theet text out out
loud as a blessing which is a you know a
10 Century blessing that you will get it
into your heart and at the most
unexpected moments uh these things will
come into your mind because you have the
oral blessing from the okay
so we're are we okay anymore yeah wow
good job all right he's working really
hard to get this ready for you so you
should thank him somay all right uh part
two meaning now that we finished uh how
to achieve perfect meditation which will
continue on Friday and Saturday right uh
now that you know how to meditate
perfectly I'm going to teach you he says
the essence of wisdom itself which is
called hot
say means
special uh Tong means to see PL Tong is
a special kind of insight into how
reality works it's piano Reaves in the
corridor just before he holds his hand
up he gets PL pong he sees into the
program and he sees how he can he can
make the bullet St okay that's called in
in
is
the
isana so this in Sanskrit is
called
sayana it's not theana or I don't know
that's a corruption that happened about
18 centuries ago okay uh so there are
three uh sections to his explanation of
how to get into the guts of of the
program that's running your world
right I will explain to
you why you
personally don't exist in the way you
thought right number
two then I will explain to you why all
the other stuff around you doesn't exist
in the way you
thought this is not some philosophical
uh
exercise all right if you could
understand how you really are you could
change
your everything about you and if you
understood how other things in the world
why they happen really you could change
them War hunger poverty death itself you
could change them if you understood
their the program
okay and then I'm going to lead you into
how to apply that in a deep state of
meditation the way you get to the
program can only be through deep
meditation you go into deep meditation
you fool around with a program you come
out and weird stuff happens right cool
stuff
happens my my teacher asked me to do an
experiment to see if I had really
reached the code all right and it was
just uh what do you call artificial
experiment he said
uh Mike I want you to prove to yourself
that you have unlocked this code you
know I said okay R what do you want me
to do you like fly in the sky or you
know what would you like me to do he
says you go to Manhattan and start a
million-dollar business I'm like R
that's like the worst thing you could do
to me you know I have no interest in
business I don't like business people I
don't like money I don't need money I
don't want money I don't want to have
those things I'm happy in the monastery
I have a tiny little room I've lived
here for 10 20 years I don't need
anything I don't want it he says yeah
but you have to prove to yourself that
you really understood the code and then
you're going to teach it to other people
and they're going to ask you have you
have you understood the code and then
you're going to say yes and then they're
going to say prove it and then you're
going to say well I can't you know so he
said you go to New York you started M do
Company by tweaking the code you just to
prove to yourself and other people later
on okay then they maybe they'll listen
to you now so I went to manhatt with no
experience no training no knowledge I
didn't even know how to get the
manhatt
uh and we started a company and we gave
away the money to refugees right the
company reached a quar billion dollars
last year it's the fastest growing
company in the history of New York City
it doubled every year for 15
years uh and I worked halftime I worked
six months a year three days a week
right and just tweaking all go in deep
meditation go into the code tweak it and
then go home and relax and do your gy
studies you see uh so you can do it
anything you want you can use
it I I think I think it's good to use it
to to do some kind of experiment in your
own life tweak something that you want
to happen I had a birth defect in my Poe
I fixed it with I tweak that also right
now I just
ballet I couldn't walk on that point uh
and uh stuff like that you know prove to
yourself that it work sometime all right
that's the point and then use it to fix
Iraq and Afghanistan and and hunger in
Africa and things like that do a little
experiment and then do a big experiment
do something that means more more in the
world right okay
very very beautiful he divides his
explanation of how reality Works into
two parts he says there's reality that
you encounter in deep deep meditation in
extremely deep meditation there's the
code of reality that you encountered
there it's called it's called like the
sky it's called Sky meditation okay it's
called Sky meditation and and you
you you uh it's the direct perception of
Ultimate Reality it's called like
like like the Crystal Sky in front of
your eyes something like that okay
then jto means after you
see the real workings of reality deeply
for the first time it takes maybe 20
minutes right when you come out
all these cool things happen to you you
can see 500 years into the future you
can meet
Angels you have ultimate love for every
creature you see every living being on
all planets for just for a few
starters uh that's called jto the next
hours uh after you see the program
directly for the first time is called
j g means illusory and that's a long
story right but basically it means
that after that you realize that nothing
was the way you thought it was right
after that you realize that nothing was
the way you thought it was now when you
look at a pen you almost directly see
the day you gave a pen to Rebecca you
see so your whole experience of your
life is much different you don't think
oh I have to order some more of these on
the Internet or you know I hope the
factory in Japan hasn't closed or I
wonder if that stationary store in
Manhattan is still selling boxes of
these so I can get some more you don't
think like that you look at the pen and
automatically comes into your mind I
should be more generous to keep these
pens going you see what I mean you don't
see it as the way that you used to see
it and
then when you come out of the direct
perception you go back to
seeing less than Ultimate Reality but
you know you're you're not seeing
Ultimate Reality you know you're wrong
you go back to seeing things slightly
wrong because you can't help yourself
but you know you're wrong all right it's
like the difference between not knowing
you're wrong when you're wrong and
knowing you're wrong when you're wrong
in jto you know you're wrong when you're
wrong right and then you spend the next
500 years or so uh getting it
right which involves deep insights into
how things work and many many
experiments like that come in and then
your mind changes right and then later
on you're into Ultimate Reality directly
all the time but it takes some time and
during that time it's cool because you
have all these cool insights for example
that nothing works Etc
right and weird things start to happen
we were talking about the other night
uh cool stuff starts to happen British
Airways calls you brsh Airways has
43,000 employees 12 billion non company
they call you they say could you come
teach this stuff to our employees you
know and you're like what they're like
come to London we'll fly you in bring a
couple people with you we'll teach you
to our staff this reality tweaking thing
because we want to be
successful and and we did we went right
uh started teaching them it's cool so
things start happening weird stuff
starts to happen cool stuff happy stuff
all
[Music]
right number
one uh in order to understand how we go
into that Sky meditation right where you
see all all things Ultimate Reality
Ultimate Reality is not a positive thing
ultimate reality is the lack of
something all right Ultimate Reality is
a lack of
something is there an African elephant
sitting in this church right
now no okay so that's that's the lack of
elephant reality in this church right
now is it positive thing or a negative
thing yeah it's the absence of something
right
is the thing which isn't here something
which generally speaking exists in this
world or
not no I mean if I say is there a lack
of elephant in this
room
yeah do elephants exist generally
speaking in our world
yeah now I ask you another question is
there a two-headed purple 20 3 and 1/2
foot elephant rampaging through this
church at this
moment no cat you didn't turn around to
check okay I I was watching her okay
she's got the best view of the aisle you
know I mean if we had a trouble with an
elephant in the church you'd want her to
at least check right why didn't you turn
around to check if there was a
two-headed purple 23 and 1/2t elephant
rampaging to the
church yeah because they just aren't
something that we have to worry about
they don't exist in this world generally
speaking all right there's no such thing
all right you you didn't have to turn
around to see if there was one in this
church because no such thing exist
right that's the same way Ultimate
Reality is Right Ultimate Reality is the
absence of something in the world that
never could have been here anyway
what's
that what's an example of one of those
things what's what's an example of one
of those things that never could have
been in the room
anyway a pen that yeah a pen that was
coming this
way point to the pen point to the pen
ready point to the pen everybody point
to the pen all right now put your arm
down now point to the a pen which was
not created by my kindness to other
people that's emptiness and that's
Ultimate Reality cool got
it where is the pen how many pens are
there in the world that didn't come from
being nice to other people zero yeah
zero all
right those kinds of pens that never
existed and never could exist are what
we call Gaga can say Gaga
gaka means the thing that was never
there and actually couldn't be there
that you always thought was there okay
the thing that couldn't be there that
you always thought was
there if you believe that you can only
get pens by being kind and sharing them
with others would you fight with someone
else about a pen No would it be possible
to fight with someone else for a pen if
you believe truly believe that the only
way to get a pen is to share it with
other people could you fight for oil
supplies in the world with China right
could you have a war which is coming
right very possible you know there are
Generals in China who said we could blow
We There are Generals in China who have
already calculated that there are not
enough bullets in all the American
Army's uh Reserves to shoot uh the
amount of Chinese they could send to
California there are Generals in China
who have already calculated that even if
every bullet hit a person and killed
them there wouldn't be enough bullets in
the United States to stop their whole
Army okay it could come right it could
come this thing could come and you know
the Americans are having warships off
their Coast now South China Sea on
exercises that's like putting a Chinese
warship off of San Diego I mean it's a
little bit belligerant right
so it's very possible that a war could
happen over oil supplies it's very
possible thing right it's a scary
possible
thing what's the only way to get oil
supplies for your
country share them with other people see
it's the same with pens you just got to
go to another scale right you got to go
to a larger scale the only only way to
get new supplies of renewable energy for
your country are to share the current
supplies of energy with other countries
in need right that's the only way right
if everybody in the United States and
China understood that could there be a
war over oil between the two countries
it's not possible all right so we have
stuff I mean December we're going from
month to China right we've been working
in China for 5 years or something and
and we're working in the United States
for a little bit
more uh but if we could change the
understanding of all the people in each
country and if they understood that oil
only came from sharing energy with other
countries in need then a war would not
be possible you see so these ideas are
very powerful and these ideas are not
just some kind of what do you call it
new age discuss you know these are
powerful
ideas you will get more supplies of
renewable energy for your country the
more you share what you have with other
countries that's all
okay oil whichever came to your country
without helping another country
is it doesn't even exist there's no such
thing all
[Music]
right when you fight with another
country over oil supplies do those oil
supplies ever
exist the oil supplies that you
perceive when you fight with another
country over oil supplies suppes do
those oil supplies exist in the way you
think they do no no there's no such oil
supplies that's the weird thing people
have wars over third it's 23 and 1/2t
two headed purple
elephants really people have wars over
things that don't exist that's gaka okay
gaka that's gaka gaka means something
you thought was there that wasn't there
all along right and the entire pain
suffering and anxiety trouble of six
billion human creatures is an
accident all directed towards things
which never even existed
Phantoms right just Phantoms everything
the world is worried about and
everything the world works for and
especially everything the world fights
over never existed in the first place
that's the huge irony of of our life
it's bad that people are suffering in
the world getting old dying fighting
going hungry that's a bad thing the fact
that it's all a mistake and unnecessary
is is is a thousand times worse
[Music]
right some guy breaks through a plate
glass window at uh Scottdale mall to hug
a lady in a fur
coat and and and slashes his body with
the glass
actually you know out of intense love
for the lady in the fur coat he breaks
through the plate glass window Cuts
himself up to hug this beautiful lady in
a fur coat who is a
mannequin and when he gets through the
glass with all that
pain I don't know I don't think it's so
much fun with a am all
right that's what's happening
means
uh ascertaining that it must be a
certain way we'll get to it
[Music]
later and
then that the last two points are ways
of proving that things don't exist the
way you thought you will find out that
things were not one thing the way you
thought and you will find out that
things were not plural things the way
you f that's all those are the things
we're going to discuss this week okay
those are the things we're going to
discuss to get to an understanding of
where reality really comes from
okay we'll go for a few more minutes
then we'll take a break all right
because I know it's been a
[Music]
while you actually got through half a
page
[Music]
a big part of the reason to learn how
reality works at its foundation is to
remove negative emotions from the human
mind permanently right that's called in
Sanskrit
van near means out van means blow van
came into ventilation wind uh words like
that okay fan they all come from Van uh
so near Van means to blow out something
and what you're blowing out is your
negative emotions desire anger
jealousy all of those feelings that
negative feelings that you have
what he's
saying here is a
very number CH means the path of the
world the path of the world Shi number
CH means
uh we talked about it the other day all
right you want to make your mind calmer
right so you decide rather than having
coffee with four scoops of coffee in it
you will have coffee with three scoops
of coffee in it all right and then you
give up you drop the four scoop coffee
and you go for the three scoop coffee
and you start to feel a little calmer
right then if you want to get more com
what do you
do two
scoops all right then you get down to
one scoop then you go to
decal okay then you could go to
uh what it call the British tea uh Earl
Gray you go to Earl Gray all right then
you go
to green tea then you go to Decap green
tea with soy steam
soy uh then you go
to uh The Next Step normally for me is
uh what's that like spicy Indian tea
ruboy chai okay rhub boy has no caffeine
in it right you go to ruboy Chai but it
still gives you a little Ki you know I
mean not much then uh then you go to
peppermint and then you go to water I
mean eventually you end up at water
right does the drinking the water feel
more calm than drinking the four scoop
coffee did you feel progressively more
calm
as you dropped
caffeine I me normally you feel more
relaxed uh you sleep much better even
drinking one cup of coffee a day screws
up most people sleep and they never get
it right they said I can't sleep I said
do you drink coffee they say yes I said
just go away don't ask me that uh you
know but the point
is that kind of approach what we just
call relative relatively happier okay
relatively happier is a good translation
of shiraki number 10 you feel more Cal
with three scoops coffee than you did
with Four Scoops coffee but you're still
a nervous person you didn't solve
anything relatively speaking you're only
90% as nervous as you were before and
you were a wreck before so now you're
90% of a wreck but you feel better all
right just going through this thing
where
you cut down on the
caffeine but you don't get rid of the
caffeine okay as long as you don't get
rid of the caffeine your mind is still
uh what do you call it disturbed by the
caffeine right it's just less Disturbed
than it was before so you feel better
that's
called means this is the world's
approach to things
uh means all you're doing is suppressing
your negative emotions you're not
dealing with them you're not stopping
them uh you drink less coffee you'll get
less upset in traffic but the minute you
start with more coffee you'll get more
upset again it's only a temporary fix
gold NBA means you are just suppressing
your negative emotions you are not uh
stopping them at the root you are not
cutting the root out of that all
right if you do a nice meditation for a
half hour
on your breath then when you get up you
will be less likely to get angry for the
next
hour uh 3 hours later you'll probably
get as angry as you ever got before it's
not an ultimate meditation it's
ultimately it's not helpful it just
suppresses the negative emotions
temporarily it doesn't treat the root of
the negative emotions and the negative
emotions come back when the meditation
wears on right we are looking for a
meditation which would permanently
change the very capacity of anger to
grow in the human mind all right and
that's a different meditation all right
here we
[Music]
go we are looking for a style of
meditating which would actually get into
the very Foundation of our negative
emotions and Destroy them at the root
right we don't want a meditation which
makes us less likely to get angry or
which makes us less angry for a few
hours or less capable of anger for a few
hours we would like a meditation which
destroys the very seeds of anger within
the human mind we would like a
meditation which after we got good at it
we would be incapable of being irritated
by other people okay
yeah all right that I mean we're talking
something much deeper we would like to
make a fundamental change in the human
mind which which no longer allows you to
get angry even under the even under
compelling circumstances you know
someone could be cutting your hand with
a razor BL and you wouldn't get
upset we would like to find by the way
that doesn't mean that you shouldn't
take steps to stop them from cutting
your hand with a razor blank but you
would be calm and happy and peaceful you
wouldn't feel upset or angry right and
actually you'd be better at stopping
them than if you were upset
[Music]
uh I'm watching the time for you okay I
am going to give you a
break there are deeper states of
meditation than the level of meditation
you require to tweak
reality got
it all right I'll say it again there's a
certain level of meditation you have to
get to to tweak the program that runs
your world reality itself there are even
deeper states of meditation than that
okay but we don't need that all right
there's no reason to go to them all
right get to the there's a certain
reachable like medium level of
meditation you can get to if you get to
that you have access to the program a
certain Stillness of mind will grant you
access to the program there are deeper
levels of meditation where the mind
becomes even more still but we don't
need them we just need to get to the
point of Stillness where we can access
the program and and change reality we
don't need to go through the thousand
levels of of deeper meditation that
there are because there's no function of
those they don't do anything get to the
amount of deep meditation that you need
to remove anger permanently from your
mind that's enough
that's enough that level of meditation
by the way is extremely difficult to
reach in one like that right but just so
you know there are deeper ones right
okay I'll say this quote and then we'll
stop and we'll
[Music]
take this is a ancient text called the
the praise of those things which are
which are worthy of
[Music]
praise the praise of those things which
are worthy of
Praise people who follow your teaching
who's
teaching Buddha it's the Buddha okay
this Ancient Ancient
book they don't even achieve the actual
level of the first uh Gana stage okay
there's eight stages of deep
meditation uh four called uh form rum
four called formless real and the first
one is divided into uh Mushi which means
the actual first one and then there's
sort of a little preliminary the first
one called
[Music]
it's not even the first of the eight
deep levels of deep meditation it's it's
the be it's the preliminary to that but
that's the level you need to get to to
tweak the program that's all you need to
get to you don't even need to get to the
actual stage number one much less the
other side right that's what he's saying
so
they don't even achieve the main level
of level number one much less the other
seven but
doig but what do you call
that I'll give you the circumstance you
tell me what we call it I don't know
what to call it uh you are what's the
guy that played James Bond that I didn't
like so much after
sh yeah Roger Moore
anyway so you know there's a huge
diamond in a in a museum somewhere he
did some movie The King what name The
Thomas Crown Affair right him was it
him yeah he's worth
right just like eminent James bun I mean
anyway uh so he and this lady decide to
steal this big diamond or something like
that I don't remember uh it was a not
memorable movie but anyway he they
decide to steal this diamond and then
there's all these cameras on the diamond
right and there's all these guard
security guards watching The Diamond so
m m and they steal it right they get it
mik shindu means how do you say that in
English under the eyes of all the guards
and the cameras it it means under the
eyes yeah Al in their not that's good
who said that yeah from under the nose
of the guards in the security camer so
this scripture says from under the nose
of the Demons who would stop people from
reaching Enlightenment you steal
Enlightenment like they're all watching
you and out from under their noses you
get in line right how's
that you stop the pain of the world you
stop the pain of the world sneaking
under the under the noses of all the
demons in the world
right without reaching without reaching
the higher states of
meditation just reaching the the
preliminary level of the first form
realm medication which is not a very
high medication but it's enough to
access the
program okay you just earned a break
from under the eye
somebody uh we're doing a big sale we're
not doing a
big
huh there may be a big sale I mean
that's
lame
okay uh I was a little disted yeah I
know I know I know uh anyway there's a b
sale we we do B sales during these
teachings uh the the money goes to send
young people to Tibetan Monastery for a
month to study and then they come back
and teach people cool stuff like this
when they get old huh oh Rebecca who's
in charge of the bag sales says please
overpay for all the things so like it's
not a problem if you pay $20 for a
single cookie and give half of it to
me okay uh have a nice break if you'd
like to say hi or you have a personal
question I'll be sitting here we'll take
about a 10 minute break there's a sign
here that I'm supposed to announce
something wow who did that yeah anyway
Bliss machine is an album that was done
my students at our
University quite a good Johnny mainly
it's a nice album I actually listened to
the first few song I got to that cowboy
song and I kind of give up anyway uh
it's $10 all the money is going to
support the we have 40 people going into
a threeyear silent retreat at the end of
December they are building their own
cabins with their own money and then
they are donating those cabins to Future
gener generations of meditators they
won't be living in them they're donating
them so she's like the farthest behind
of anybody except for these other two
wom uh but uh she's all that she's got
up is four plywood walls and she's got
to get moving in the next month so the
proceeds from this spectacular album
which is only $10 are going to Coco's
meditation card okay
uh if you want to swipe Liberation out
from under the nose of all
obstructing
demons uh you're going to have
to Define to yourself what is the real
nature of things okay you're going to
have
to come to an understanding right
[Music]
if you don't come to an understanding of
the way reality
works you will never be able to stop
your negative emotions it's not possible
okay we have a teaching on the six
Perfections right these are the six
activities of a b first one is giving
the second one is living ethical life
third one is not getting mad when you
should the fourth is being happy about
doing good things the fifth is the
ability to meditate deeply and the sixth
is uh understanding reality all right so
he says if you don't learn about
emptiness and how things really
work then if you do the other
Perfections the first five right if you
are a generous person or you try to be
ethical or you try to stop your
anger means you will be doing so without
understanding how things really work for
example in the case of the art of not
getting angry when you should have all
right the art of not getting angry when
you should have right somebody cuts you
off in traffic right uh or someone yells
at you at work
what in the
text
means uh there's a way to practice
patience about a person who hurts you
which is ignorant right there's a way to
be good towards a person who has hurt
you which is
ignorant you you go to them you you're
calm you say you know you hurt me and
and I'm I'm really would like to ask you
not to do that right and you're
reasonable and you're calm and and you
don't yell at them and you're sweet and
and all that okay and and maybe it works
and maybe it doesn't work okay that's
the
problem maybe it works and maybe it
doesn't work that's the
problem because you have not approached
the person who's hurting you with an
understanding of the
deeper sources of reality right you you
haven't in your own mind approached this
person who's hurting you with an
understanding of where they came from so
the the patience demonstrated by a
person who understands where the world
is coming from is different from the
patience demonstrated by a person who
doesn't know where the world is coming
from the patience of a person who
doesn't understand where the world is
coming from Will always break down at
some point they cannot be maintained
past a certain level of
abuse right someone cuts you off once
you can be patient someone cuts you off
twice you can be patient someone cuts
you off bumps your Fender you know turns
around and hits you in the back at some
point your patience will break if you
don't understand the deeper reality of
this person who's bothering you right
what's the deeper
reality I have produced this
person this person is coming because of
some behavior of my own the whole focus
of a well-trained spiritual person turns
away from the world to themselves okay
the whole focus of correcting things
turns away from negotiating with the
people who are hurting you to examining
yourself and seeing how did I do
something like that before and that
exercise makes you an extremely mentally
healthy and happy person right the
exercise someone is constantly
complaining to you okay all the time and
it it bothers you and it's
unpleasant and you don't have a well
educated
practitioner doesn't even think about
talking to them or negotiating with them
or or explaining to them how much
they're complaining is hurting them they
don't even have to they don't even think
about it they think oh where did this
person come from oh they're complaining
they must come
from complaining in some way and that
was done by me so who do I complain to
and who can I stop complaining to and
then it will just shut them down like a
faucet being turned off you know like
people are trying to plug a a hole in
the faucet and they could go under the
sink and just turn it off you see
they're standing there with 23 towels
and pushing pushing the faucet and
trying to stop it and just open the
little door under there and turn the
valve and it's off you see turn the
valve is you're
complaining right so go to the source
and turn it off and then the person will
startop complaining you see it's very
beautiful a well trained
spiritual person who understands where
reality comes from their patience is on
a different level from the patience of
other people because their patience is
infinite it cannot be
shaken the worse things get the more
they check themselves out the worse the
other person gets the more they examine
their own heart and make themselves
sweeter so the worse the world gets the
sweeter they get it's it's cool and it's
fun
okay no negotiation no no discussions no
confrontations no tension no you don't
have to talk to them just find out what
you're doing that's similar and stop it
and then they will change or they'll go
have a hard time okay
[Music]
I love this metaphor this is one of the
most beautiful images in all of uh
scripture by the way we're going to go
half an hour over get used to it 9:30 we
still won't finish tonight's lesson but
at least you'll be able to do like one
or two homework questions and you'll
feel better and I won't do if you come
to a homework question on number six
that I didn't explain just leave it
blank for now all right cuz we're not
going
to he compares the journey uh to
Enlightenment to a bird flying in the
sky to an eagle flying in the sky right
he Compares your journey to
Enlightenment to an eagle flying through
the sky and he says that eagle needs two
Wings right a a glorious phoenix bird
with One Wing don't count for much all
right they can't go anywhere so he says
you need two Wings what are
they uh one one is called top which
means method which means all the
kindnesses that you are going to be
doing generosity to others serving
others being patient with others being
joyful about serving others even
meditation okay these are all the things
you're going to be doing to help other
people that's One Wing it's called
method doing stuff right that's One
Wing then the other Wing is called
understanding what's going
on you know and we gave the example
of patience with
a complaining person around you patience
with a person around you who's
complaining on okay how how can you
change
them change your own complaint examine
yourself for what are you complaining
about all
right this powerful left say this
powerful right hand wing of what you
would call conventional patience it's
like a single wing and it can't get you
anywhere you need the other Wing where
you understand the nature of the person
who is complaining to you that you are
being patient about that they are coming
from you you cannot solve the problem
without understanding that the
complaining person is coming from your
complaining that understanding is the
other way you need both ways you need
patience yes but you got to know what
the heck's going on the
habitations and those are two WIS
understanding and then stuff that you do
called they're called method and
wisdom with with any one of the two
Wings by the way there are people who
have this Wing without this Wing they
are like deep into emptiness they
understand the void you know they go
into the void regularly but they get
around a slightly irritating person and
it breaks down
immediately you see or they don't do
anything to help other people really
they just kind of talk about ESS all the
time right they have this wing and not
this wi got it some people have this
wing and not this wi all right to get
your Enlightenment you got to have both
of you need
he he calls the method compassion acts
of
compassion but they must be United with
in understanding of where stuff is
coming
from you cannot separate the two you
cannot train yourself in compassion
without training yourself in where the
world is coming from and you can't train
yourself in where the world is coming
from unless you train yourself in
compassion
would be like a a beautiful phoenix bird
the only one I've seen recently was in
uh Harry
po uh I mean the phoenix flying and all
that I mean try to imagine them flying
uh with one bird there's some joke about
a duck with one leg in water what is
that oh yeah somebody says G do you want
a hot chocolate
and then I either say does the pope wear
a beanie or my dad used to say does a
bear poof in the
woods uh but I heard this other one the
other day it's does a onelegged duck
swim in circles anyway you don't want to
be like a a phoenix with one WI
what is
that
okay maybe the most famous short piece
that ever wrote 14 verses that's one of
the
verses if you don't possess the wisdom
which understands why and how things are
happening
you can meditate and master the the
attitudes of enunciation and love you
can Master renunciation and compassion
but but
see you will not be able to cut the root
of the pain of the world you will not be
able to stop the pain of the you will
not be able to cut it
Source therefore they
those of you who
know why he has two instrumentals is
interesting okay he says mean you pay
because you will not be able to cut it
therefore okay like it's redundant it's
a fault of composition it's not allowed
in Buddhist scripture why has he written
two different words for
therefor you think
about about
you must come to you must seek the means
of grasping dependent origination okay
depend origination is a fancy longwinded
word for how stuff
happens let's change
it how stuff
happens seek seek the knowledge of why
things how things
happen that's what said we have try to
do
that I love this I really love this next
part all right shenya it's like jelly
going what she does she gets up here and
she starts screaming what does she do
all right or something yes yes
yes I love this
say
sorry
say is it up there
somewhere yeah where is that yeah the
second line in the middle
say we never heard of that
right okay uh this is
co if you really get it when I
say the person who's complaining about
you or to you all the time has only come
from your own complaining right got it
when I when I say that thing you know
and and you're sort of like attracted to
it you
think you're not even sure about it tet
here tet the word tet is there a tet up
there
somewhere at the end of the first line
Tet means you get a little suspicion
that I might be
right not even you're not even sure okay
you're not even sure and you haven't
accepted it yet Texon means a little
suspicion that it might be true all
right if you just get a little tiny
suspicion that it might be true that
every negative thing that ever happened
to you and every negative person you
ever met was a mirror of your own
behavior right if you just get a little
taste of that and begin to think it
might be possible that's ton soon need
to eat the doubt it means to entertain
the possibility that the last irritating
person you met and the 3,000 before
him all came from the way you are
behaving
then drle means I need
a okay listen carefully
that's strong got it it's on PE here we
go
again sorry cat Okay
uh that's you you gave it it up for Sho
okay you can always remember Sho means
you tear the fabric of reality you tear
the fabric of suffering you put an un
you put an irreparable tear into the
reality of the suffering of the world
around you and that can only get bigger
you you tear a little you put a little
tear into
the network of suffering around the
fabric the very fabric of the reality of
the suffering of the world you put a
little tear irreparable tear and it can
only get bigger and then you will rip
the suffering of the world apart it's
very
beautiful just if you suspect then I
might be right you don't even have to
believe me just if you start saying
H okay you only get then got it who goes
to all
right I love it you put you start a tear
you start a rent rent rent in the fabric
of reality that is never again the same
you will never again be the same you can
never I'm putting a curse on on you
today I'm putting a curse on you you can
never really believe that any bad thing
or bad person you ever meet in the
future is not a mirror of your own
behavior again I curse you T tonight now
I curse
you you can never fully hate another
person again you know you can never
fully blame another person again I curse
you I curse you with that okay you
always have this little doubt that maybe
it's something you
did where were
we kind of here oh yeah
uh uh and in
time will come to destroy the loto okay
where does the name of s Monastery come
from
what's s
mean yeah s means hail hail hailstones
big
hailstones and uh we debate with the
other great monasteries G and de right
what does de mean it means a pile of
rice d means rice po means pile it it
means their Monastery was nestled on
this White Mountain before it got
destroyed uh it was called deadpol okay
so when we debate with them in the
monastic debates we say we are Sarah you
are G you know we are hail storm that
crushes the rice pattern you know and
then they say yes but then the the hail
always melts away that's and the rice
remain you know and so
anyway CH means l means crops which have
been destroyed by hell right if you live
in a country like toet where the what do
you call it the amount of food is is
very fragile it's it's what 20,000 ft
higher 18,000 ft High to grow a crop is
difficult and then just when you get the
barley growing you know then there's
this big hell storm and it destroys
everything hearing me say once that the
person who most irritates you in your
life right now is a direct result of
your own behavior will in time be a hail
storm that destroys all your
s like a rice crop under under these
huge stones of
[Music]
H there it is
again this is beautiful she is the 400
verses written by AR's dear
student okay and he
said those who lack sufficient goodness
will not even get the suspicion that gim
Michel might have said something correct
you see those who lack extremely heavy
Good
Karma he get up and say look the last
person that you that you who complain to
you all the time came from your
complaining just to hear those words and
to give them what do you call to
entertain any truth to
them is a sign that you have
extraordinary Good Deeds you have you
have higher Good Karma than than
hundreds of thousands of other
people young T young means people
without extraordinary Good Karma will
not even entertain the possibility that
I was speaking the truth God
[Music]
but even if you have a little doubt that
it might be correct if you have the
least suspicion that I might be saying
something true when I say that every bad
thing that I have to do is coming from
you you are
tearing a a r a r you are ring the
fabric of suffering itself and it will
never be the same it'll never come back
to the where it was before I said those
words all right okay
[Music]
uh there was a thing called
sock uh with regard to developing
meditation that was the six things you
needed before you even sat down so means
you have to gather together these things
why is a religious ceremony called
the you gather together the offerings
and you gather together the people the
offerings themselves are called so okay
do offer the to so to means a
gathering before you even try to
meditate on a cush you must gather
together certain conditions and we
listed them there were six and there
were five right for example the right
kind of place and the right kind of
friends and the right kind of
instructions you need to gather these
things together
preconditions that need to be gathered
together he says for wisdom you're also
going to have to gather together certain
conditions for this as
well you're going have to collect
together certain things
you are going to have to find a
person who truly grasps the meaning of
the teachings on emptiness in the
scriptures okay two personal experience
you're going to have to find a person
who not doesn't only know what the books
say but has had a personal experience of
those things you're going to have to
find a person like that
then and then you're going to have to go
to them and listen to them teaching
right we need the Duma Duma means uh
like K Duma it means uh instructions
advice
teaching this is a very beautiful thing
okay in the
monastery you don't study the highest
teachings on emptiness for 12 years it
takes 12 years before you're allowed to
to study maika higher maik you spend the
first 12 years on on Lower
I'll be some the first 12 years of your
monastic career are 12 years spent on a
50 page book called the ornament of
realizations by AR you can memorize it
in about a year or something you know
and then you spend 12 years on 50 pages
four pages a year you spend 12 years
then you're allowed to go to to the real
teachings on internet okay uh in between
the 12 years of lower maima and the four
years of higher maima there's a
tradition to go on
Retreat you go out you go to Ken R went
to a cave and and did a retreat and he
almost died there there's a beautiful
story he almost died in that he came
very close to dying uh but in that
experience he cleaned away the negative
seeds he had in his mind that before he
open the book on emptiness see so the
idea is you go off on a long retreat
before you're allowed to open
the before you're even allowed to look
at the book you have to do a special
Retreat to get rid of all Bad Karma
seeds in your mind and to collect new
good kic seat you cannot approach the
subject of emptiness with without
undertaking
very deep uh activities and projects to
to serve other
people if you want to approach the
subject of emptiness go teach yoga in a
prison which you're going to learn about
on
Sunday okay it looks like the chaplain
of the prison where we work is going to
give us a small talk on suay or go uh
raise money for the three-year Retreat
food
all right which is our next
problem uh or go raise some funds for
the people who are typing in the
scriptures for example okay before you
approach the subject of emptiness you
will have to do some powerful Goods
Karma collection and some powerful Bad
Karma removal and and in Tibet it was a
retreat okay in in nowadays in the
monastery my class when we got to
maika we were required to leave the
monastery for 3 months and go do some
charitable project Hands-On service of
sick people or poor people or you know
we w't allowed to touch this book until
we had done three months of service for
other people it's beautiful it's a nice
custom so so so J means collect new Good
Karma purify your old Bad Karma then
study emptiness this is a precondition
to study emptiness as much
as
uh finding a good meditations place is a
prerequisite for studying sh
it also you are going to have to do a
lot of asking of help from holy
beings that's a prerequisite for
studying happiness like go
home just in your this is all done in
your mind right in the privacy of your
own mind and it's fun to talk to Holy
beings in your own mind okay don't think
you're crazy you're not like s Sam or
anything all right uh go home uh just
talk to them you know what I found out
with Bella where is Bella like when you
need her she's not
here okay that's Bella in in L Ora's
hands okay like I found out this thing
with Bella you know like I was there the
night the three nights she was
born and uh you know and
then for months I was going up there and
say
hello you know and I'm trying to get her
to smile she's just
like you know and then uh then one day I
just went up to her and I said Bella you
have to smile at me you know like I'm
not going to do this big talk to you
anymore let's just talk man to man you
know like I want you to smile at me once
a while so you have a problem with that
and she she
go and then
uh it's the same with the Holy beings
okay like just talk to them just just
talk they can read your mind right they
can read your mind so just sit down say
look uh Gish Michel starting to
hopefully he'll get to the subject
um he's going to be teaching emptiness
and I I just want to you put in a word
you know can you put in a good word for
me you know like I I'm going to be
studying emptiness and I I would
appreciate it if you would bless my mind
right now tonight you know cuz he might
start tomorrow or the next day okay just
like that have a rational don't do the
Google boo boo thing don't
say that's like booo you know
just talk to them rationally in your
head say you know I love you very much
you're the most they they're talking
about your llama
okay means your llama indivisible from
your guardian angel
L your Lama indivisible from your
guardian angel same one and the same
baby I'm asking my holy sweet precious
incomparable most beautiful thing in the
universe llama Inseparable from my
guardian angel I'm asking you right now
in front of all these people to bless my
mind to teach this thing beautifully
okay and just talk to them rationally
like that sometimes out loud is fun too
in the hotel room but you got to close
the door
okay you will need all the necessary
preconditions don't ignore these things
don't jump into the book and say I don't
have to ask anybody anything and I don't
need to do a retreat and I don't need to
serve the poor with my hands or I don't
need to go to a prison and waste my time
uh just tell me what the book
says he
says told if you do that you'll never
get it you can come to the teachings you
can sit there gu you Michael can say the
same words to you that he's saying to
the person who went to the prison and
that person will get it and you won't
get it and you'll be in the same room
and you'll be sitting next to each other
and you'll be eating the same cookies
from Rebecca's B sale but you will get
it and they will okay there something
there's something about the causes what
do you call it
to the pre
conditions we're going to stop there
okay uh he's about to talk
about why did Lord Buddha teach
different kinds of En
and and which version should we
buy that's sort of a different subject
do as much of the homework as you can
number six don't stress about it please
please do the homework all these people
spending hundreds of hours to help you
become a teacher of some other people
you know a thousand years of lineage
don't let it stop here tonight you know
don't be lazy okay one little homework
with like what three questions on it I
mean are are you going to be the one who
stops a thousand year minut cuz you
didn't want to do three questions on a
Tuesday night when you had the whole day
from off
tomorrow
okay just do it and then teach it all
right
promise isans I
swear in the diamond business it means I
swear same will you teach this to other
people okay then you have to do your
homework